so I came about a year ago and I'm sorry
it took me so long to come back we're
just really busy we have a lot of things
going on in many countries and if you
remember if you came last year we talked
about a book called the diamond cutter
sutra and this is a teaching that was
given by Lord Buddha two and a half
thousand years ago during the Millennium
there was some talk that the world might
blow up so I decided I would like to be
where he taught that diamond cutter
Sutra so I went to India and on the
stroke of midnight I was sitting in
travesty at this park of jetavana and I
was waiting for the mushroom cloud and I
thought it would be a good place to you
know celebrate and nothing happened but
I waited and it was really nice to be
there the reason why we found that place
is that there was a Chinese monk named
chuan Tong who travelled he walked for
17 years through India and he visited
all the holy places and he counted his
steps going each direction and he wrote
a book called which later became called
Journey to the West and he counted the
steps to shrawasti and then people dug
their about I think 20 30 feet down they
found the city of Shabbos dinner and the
garden in which the Buddha taught the
diamond cutter and it's been I think
next to the Bible one of the most
printed works in history
it's the oldest printed book in the
world if the diamond cutter in Chinese
language and you know the way I started
learning it was you know in the
monastery you do a thing called shut
down shut down means every I don't know
week or something one of the families in
the congregation will invite you to
their home
and then there's a deal that goes on
like they will cook you a good meal if
you recite the diamond cutter suits are
really nice so you know I went with like
six or seven months and in the main monk
took out the diamond cutter Sutra this
is the first time I saw it and he split
the pages up between all of us you know
and I was like I thought we were gonna
read it together and he said no no you
know that will take too long we get
lunch afterwards he said we're all gonna
recite different pages at the same time
and I'm like you sure and he said they
don't know what you're saying anyway you
know and I'm like okay so slowly I got
to know the diamond cutter Sutra in
sixths and because I had to I had to
read it most the time I got different
parts and I started to really enjoy it
and later it became mine I think my
favorite book and about I don't know two
years ago we have a project to save the
ancient books of Asia and we've we've
typed in I think we just passed our 30th
year we just finished all the books from
India there are 5000 surviving
manuscripts from India and we just
finished them about a year ago and now
we're typing in the 200,000 Tibetan
commentaries and that will take another
hundred years
and we started translating them and
that's on schedule for 150 more years
and the first 10,000 books we we have a
plan and I started to read an ancient
commentary on the diamond cutter by
someone named Kamala Sheila and he lived
about 1300 years ago in India and he
wrote a beautiful commentary on the
diamond cutter which was lost in India
and lost in China and the only surviving
copies are in Tibetan and so I I was
able to get a copy and I started reading
it and I thought it was really
extraordinary so I you know I started
teaching it and I realized it would take
me
for sessions to finish it so we started
doing it at the amount retreat center
and we did I don't know 10 days at a
time and we finished the first quarter
last year and I came to New York like
just after that so it's fresh in my mind
and I taught it here and now tonight I'd
like to share with you the second part
of the combi Sheila's commentary and
then we'll do the third and fourth parts
later if we're all still here and you
have a reading I hope everyone got a
reading and comic Aquila designs his
commentary to the diamond cutter Sutra
in meditations like five minute
meditations that you can continue to do
after tonight if you like this little
book that you have is a guide to those
meditations and what I did was trying to
match each meditation to a photo because
personally I find it easier to remember
what's the next meditation by just
remembering the photo so I can remember
the photo and then I try to remember
what with photo was about and I
encourage you you know tonight and
tomorrow they're different subjects okay
we'll do half tonight half tomorrow and
I encourage you to make it a meditation
practice okay so you can we'll practice
tonight the meditations and then you can
try them on your own at home and I think
if you if you do one every you can
change it like two times you can do two
a week there's 26 meditations in here
that'll get you through a quarter of the
year and then you start over again okay
and I think you'll find that they're
very beautiful meditations and you know
they're about 1,300 years old and and I
find them very hopeful helpful I do them
often I did them on the plane yesterday
and I think you'll find them very
helpful okay
so we're picking up halfway through the
diamond cutter Sutra I'm gonna be
telling you you know what Buddha is
saying at any particular moment
and then we're gonna talk about what
comma Sheila says about it and then
we'll be doing a meditation on it each
meditation is only like five minutes or
something like that so tonight just so
we have time we'll we'll stick to about
five minutes per meditation and you know
and then if you enjoy them I think they
will make a big impact on your life if
you keep doing them just like five 10
minutes every morning before you go to
work or something I think you will
something amazing will happen to you and
I think the people who tried it last
year found that big changes occurred in
their life okay
so I encourage you to keep that little
booklet and I encourage you to to do
these meditations this year okay in the
next few months start okay first thing
we're gonna pick up in the middle of the
sutra commonly sheila light lays out the
sutra in different sections okay the
very first section is where you know he
sets the scene in traversed in north
india and people are talking and and one
of the disciples of the buddha called
savuti he comes to Lord Buddha and says
okay what are we supposed to do how are
we supposed to think how is supposed to
practice and then the whole sutra is
lord buddha's answer to sue booty so
karma Sheila says really the first part
of the whole book the whole sutra you
can say the subject is bodhichitta
bodhichitta means the desire to help the
whole world you know the desire to to
bring the whole world happiness so the
very first section of the sutra Lord
Buddha says de cebú T and he makes up a
word which doesn't exist in Sanskrit or
Tibetan
and he says nirvana sighs people you
should Nirvana sighs people and
somebody's like what he says you know
like Nirvana sighs them and then he
discussed you know what does it mean to
Nirvana sighs some money and the process
of Nirvana sizing people depends on
understanding one great subject which is
emptiness or coaching in Chinese
language and I have a demonstration that
I've developed we do business seminars
all over the world last year 20,000
people came in 35 cities
twenty-something countries and I've just
developed a little demonstration to help
you understand emptiness if you
understand emptiness at the beginning
you can appreciate the diamond cutter
Sutra more that's the point of the
diamond cutter Sutra so I will
demonstrate emptiness in a very ordinary
situation and then you know for the
whole two nights you'll be ready to
understand the Sutra better okay
and it took me many years to develop
this so the men of the world had a
meeting and a couple years ago and you
know in those days women weren't allowed
to work much and we decided that we
should allow women to work and we had a
decision because they already had to
take and those days had to take care of
the children and they had to cook so you
know and that was the division of duties
in the old days the woman cooks and
takes care of the kids and the man works
and makes the money for the cooking and
the take care of the kids and then we
had the male's had a meeting you guys
weren't there and we decided to women's
rights were important that they should
be able to work also and then that would
give us time to watch Superbowl and
stuff because they would be working and
taking care of the kids and paying for
the groceries buying the groceries and
cooking so that's how it is now that's
the system now a lot of men stay home
did stuff on the internet and then the
women work cook and take care of the
kids so it's a little stressful for
women because it's difficult to do all
those things in one day and I'm thinking
of a woman who's got that situation and
and she's got an important meeting
work early in the morning you know and
her boss tells her I'd like you to come
in at 7:30 instead of 9:00 because you
know we have an international call going
on and then you the woman tells her two
kids here my two kids okay is that all
right yeah so I'm the wife okay and
you're the two kids and I'm the woman
tells the kids look mommy's been called
in early tomorrow at 7:30 I have to be
at work so I need you guys to be ready
at seven o'clock you know all your
school clothes on your homework finish
you know don't forget to put your good
shoes on and mommy will be in at 7:00
and you just were gonna just take off
and then I'll get to work on time okay
you guys agree the kids aren't you agree
yeah the kids agree then you know you
know the story the next morning mom
comes in and you know opens the door and
the kids are jumping on the bed and
they're in their pajamas you know and
you're like and then dress as fast as
you can and these kids are really bad
and they're like jumping on the bed and
then they lose their shoes because they
were jumping on the bed and then finally
mom gets to a certain point where she
says you know you had a stupidest kids
in New York you know I'm so unlucky to
have kids like not really okay but she's
like you're the two stupidest kids in
New York aid so that's like on Wednesday
then you know all the weekend comes and
and then Monday rolls around and and
she's working all day normal work day
after work he has to go do the groceries
because the husband's too lazy because
there's some important game on and you
know so she's exhausted when she comes
home but the one thing she's looking for
is a hug from her husband which is like
the only thing she really asked from him
is give me a just please give me a hug
when I get home okay you ready so I need
a husband
now it's re we're sorry can you mind it
be a husband you're you're a good New
York house I know you're here with your
son
I know you're a good husband and we're
gonna need two husband sex they Scott do
we have some light on these guys I mean
okay so they're the there's two of them
don't worry about it yet okay
they're the same one and I'm the wife
you know and I come home I'm really
really tired and exhausted and I'm just
thinking the only thing I would really
like tonight you know I don't mind I
have to make them money
I don't mind I'm working all day I don't
mind to do the the groceries you know I
don't mind that I have to cook and I'm
dragging myself home and I'm really
tired you know and I'm just thinking
about this hug I'm gonna get from my
husband when I open the door you know
why why no dinner where's dinner
okay then I'm tired you know I didn't
working all day I just want a hug you
know I'm put on my arms and they call me
okay then I if you haven't studied the
diamond cutter Sutra okay if you don't
know about emptiness what will you do
yeah you say no yes I've been working
all day I took care of the kids I is
gonna come home make you did otherwise a
hug from you
I'm not stupid you're stupid okay that's
normal if you haven't studied diamond
cutter if you don't know about emptiness
okay if you do know about emptiness
right huh
pause why
man I got caught in New York for 20
years nothing happened
what no she says I don't know why he's
yelling at me all I did was open the
door I've been working all day I didn't
say anything okay I didn't do anything I
didn't do anything I came home and it
yells at me I didn't do anything okay is
it true I didn't do anything
Frances you were better when you're a
little kid is it true I didn't do
anything
y-yeah yelled at the kids last week okay
that's how karma is planted okay you
have to understand the meaning of the
word karma karma means anything you do
or say or think okay and the way it's
planted is very interesting like I
didn't believe in karma until I heard
how it was planted when I when I yell at
the kids when I say what you're the
stupidest kids in New York when I say
you're the stupidest kids in New York
that sound enters my brain it brushes my
mind and the more anger I have the more
in imprints on my mind it makes an
imprint on my mind then after about two
three hours a seed starts to form in the
in the subconscious and that's how karma
is planted if you know how it's planted
you can believe it more you see so I
yelled at them I heard myself it made an
imprint on my mind and in about two
three hours that imprint which is called
at that point a vasana right samskaara
becomes a vaasana' after a couple hours
and that's a karmic scene okay then I
open the door week later that seeds been
cooking under the subconscious like a
watermelon seed under the dirt and then
when I open the door what happens
suddenly the seed opens okay
suddenly the seed opens and a and a and
an image of myself being yelled at is
projected out into the world and comes
back you see and that's Karma okay got
it
so what's gonna happen if they say
and I understand karma and I will I'd
tell them what they are know why cuz I'm
nice or I'm moral why not yeah I don't
want it to happen again what is it
called when it happens again in Buddhism
some sorry okay
that's son sorry so samsara is not some
theoretical you know Buddhist the Indian
thing sansara means cycle cycle of pain
I if I yell at them and tell them that
what they are which is stupid if I say
that who will hear it yeah I will hear
it okay and then that plant another seed
and then my kids act up next week that's
why they acted up the last time you see
what I mean so it becomes a cycle that
the seeds are opening in my mind and the
states are coming on in my mind so if I
understand that's by the way what's that
called Buddhism do you know there's a
long stupid name that process is called
dependent origination okay our plant
seeds in my own mind they open they
become the people around me I respond to
those people then I plant more seeds and
it goes like that okay that's called the
Wheel of Life now why did I put two
husband's up here it's because the next
day when you meet your friends you say I
met my husband I kiss came home I opened
the door and then there's a single word
you say you ready for no reason oh okay
no reason are for no reason at all he
started yelling at me I didn't do
anything you know I didn't say anything
I didn't do anything
and for noise and all he starts
screaming at me you know he call me
stupid
for no reason oh is it for no reason at
all no it's because I planted a seed
last week with the two you're good kids
no okay I've planted a seed last week
with the two kids okay so it's in
Buddhism there's no such in the diamond
kind of sutra there's no such thing as
for no reason at all it doesn't exist
it's not possible
there's
no such thing okay everything that
happens to you is coming from a seed
that you plant it before okay now I put
two husbands up here because there's two
possibilities when you come in the room
and they call you you have two choices
okay and there's two ways to look at
this situation okay one is okay he's
gonna be noise at all okay like I don't
know why he all by me I didn't do
anything okay
he's for noise you know he's mr. husband
for no reason all he's yelling at me for
no reason oh okay
now then I went to the diamond cutter
talk at Florence called Hall last night
and I found out what was really going on
and now when I walk in I realized that
he's coming from my seats and there is a
reason and it's my fault that he's
yelling at me okay he's my fault got it
so let's practice with Ori he calls me
he calls me stupid
go ahead practice it's good with your
teacher because it you're stupid and
then because I think he didn't come from
me I say no you're stupid okay and then
I plant another seed for the kids to act
up and then it goes like a cycle okay
because I don't know where he's coming
from
I don't understand where he's coming
from that he's coming from me okay got
it
now this one oh so I can also be angry
and upsetting him because he's yelling
at me no reason oh okay now this one you
know I went to the talk last night I I
learned what's correct he's coming from
my seats okay ready
yeah okay then you go to the toilet do
you know why you just calmly go to the
toilet open the door look in the mirror
you're stupid understand now I'm not
kidding
okay so that's the second reaction now I
have a question okay mister he's mister
for noise at all okay he's coming from
the seeds I planted with my used to be
bad kids okay now there's one you don't
get angry at and there's someone that
you do get angry at tell me which one is
which which one do you good upset it
yeah for no reason all I get upset at
the husband who's not my fault you see
that mean got it everybody got in so
when I get upset I the husband I have in
my mind the husband I feel is hurting me
it's the one who's not my fault got it
and this one how do I feel I feel like
sad I feel like this too bad I yelled at
my kids last week you know I'll try to
be better with my kids you know but you
don't get angry at this one because this
one's your phone you said I mean if you
fall on some water in the bathtub and
you hurt yourself but you realize it's
you who left the water there this
morning you don't get angry if you think
it was somebody else you get angry so as
long as you understand it's you who
caused it you don't tend to get angry
okay now come back I'll give you another
one one of them exists in one of them
doesn't one of them really exist in one
of them doesn't really exist tell me
which is which
yeah we know that oh no you're right
Francis okay the one who's snores you
know that that husband in Buddhism they
say meh but Panda member Yemen mmm my
humble memoir it means there's no he
never could exist can't exist now could
never exist in the future
okay the husband who is not your fault
any experience in your life which is not
your fault doesn't exist okay got it
now what do we call the absence of if we
if we say look you don't exist just go
away then what's left here but what do
we call in Buddhism emptiness okay you
can come back it's okay got it
so emptiness is not more complicated
than that okay emptiness means someone
that you thought wasn't your fault isn't
there there's no such person
there's nobody in your life from mr.
Trump down who's not your fault you see
everyone you ever met was coming from
you and the world is a perfect mirror of
your own mind and your own behavior okay
magnified by time right so this one
exists or not
who's not my fault exists or not doesn't
exist and what do you call his absence
emptiness okay so now you learn some
about emptiness emptiness means the
absence of something you thought was
there that couldn't have been there got
it so you're not losing anything when
you say things are empty because they
were never there in the first place you
just realized they weren't there you
thought they were there right somebody
who wasn't your fault
okay now according to I'll go one more
step with you in Buddhism according to
Buddhism it's impossible to overcome
anger it's not possible in the universe
for a person to overcome anger
permanently without understanding that
because you will always think they're
doing it for some reason you know that
they decided to yell at you okay so
according to Buddhism there's no
psychological method there's no
religious method to ever stop anger
forever unless you realize the person
you're angry at was never there gunning
you want to go global there's never been
a war there's never been a conflict in
the history of mankind that was not
based on people who are not there okay
all all conflict globally in history
fifty thousand years of killing people
came from anger over nothing over that
there was nothing there the person that
your country was angry at Muslims the
people you're angry at were not there
because you think they don't come from
you got it Muslims who are dangerous to
your country who don't come from you
what don't exist there's no such thing
you can put a ban on them but they're
already been there's no such thing okay
there's no such thing there's no such
thing it doesn't make any sense
you see a person who had hurt your
country who's not coming from your
unfriendly behavior doesn't exist
you see got it and in Buddhism this is
the only way to reach nirvana the
definition Arianna named Indian mother
for Bombay so sorry tango the definition
of Nirvana is noon developer stopping
your negative emotions forever because
you understood emptiness that's the
definition of Nirvana okay so the point
of the diamond cutter Sutra I just
taught you the rest is desert okay
that's emptiness okay and it's not some
kind of what is emptiness not it's not a
black hole okay you you focus you close
your eyes and you think I'm a black hole
it's not that you watch your thoughts
and they fade away and then you're empty
my mom I used to say
if that's emptiness you don't have to
study for 20 years you can just get
really drunk yeah if that's what it is
you know and then of the final version
is Oh everything's an illusion and
there's no good and there's no bad and
that's the worst version of emptiness
okay because then you'll hurt yourself
and other people okay so those are not
black is not emptiness thoughts fading
from your mind is not emptiness you know
nothing's good nothing's bad
everything's an illusion you should sit
in the corner and just be neutral it's
not emptiness okay what's emptiness is
this what we talked about okay if you
understand it you could be wildly
successful I used it in a company in New
York we got to 250 million a year from
zero and then Warren Buffett bought the
company how just understand this much
and you can do anything okay it's very
powerful that the diamond cutter Center
is not some ancient philosophy tank it's
something you can use in a positive way
you can become extremely successful in a
you know in a negative way you can just
stop your husband from being such a
anyway okay all right so don't nap so
please never forget when you're in a
heavy situation with someone okay like
your spouse seems to happen with spouses
once a while there's two of them in the
room there's always two of them in the
room one is your fault one is coming
from what you did last week to the kids
on Wednesday okay and the other one is
who noise enough and therefore noon for
the the for no reason at all doesn't
exist got it but that's the one you're
always when you're angry
it's this one that you're angry on so
anytime you have a tense moment with
another person it's it's the one who's
not there that you're feeling tense
about and the emptiness of that person
means there's no such person okay and if
you understand that you can be a happy
person for the rest of your life okay
got it
just just when something happens at home
I know it never happens but just stop
and say which one in my manner you know
which which
husband in my upset right now and you'll
find it's the one who's not there got it
now we can start the Sutra thank you to
husbands appreciate it
yeah I know your father's a star so at
this point in the Sitra we're about a
quarter way through this to turn Lord
Buddha says to his students of Buddha
it's a conversation between Buddha and
his student and he says some so is it
possible for someone to become a Buddha
and somebody says alright I guess and
then Buddha says well how do you know
and you look at somebody that they're
there a Buddha and there's special signs
of a Buddha ok Buddha's have 112 special
signs if you check their body you will
find 112 subtle signs on their body
ok there's 30 major ones sorry 32 major
ones 80 minor ones ok and when I taught
this at Diamond Mountain we had 10 days
to do it and I I taught all the science
it took like three four days we don't
have time to do that ok but the Buddha
says to his student if I meet a guy who
has all those science that only Buddha's
have is he a Buddha and Sebu T says
gasps I mean this is the weird Sutra he
says of course not
and Buddha says why and savuti says
because those signs are impossible so
that's the first exchange we're doing
tonight
ok so Lord Buddha says to his disciple
if a person has one hundred and twelve
signs on their body that only Buddhists
have are they a Buddha and savuti says
no and he says why not and he says those
signs are impossible which husband is he
talking about
yeah he's talking about for anything we
know so it also applies to the parts of
your body ok the parts of your body have
all been created by your own state of
mind ok we believe in past 9
maybe it's random maybe something blew
up from nothing
called Big Bang and then you know dust
particles banged into each other and
created your specific nose or or maybe
there's more sense to it you know maybe
there's more logic to why your body is
the way your body is but the first
meditation here which is what what's in
your book anybody doesn't have a book
raise your hand and somebody's gonna run
and give you one if you don't keep it up
they won't give you one who's gonna run
around
Hannibal since you don't have a luncheon
what's the best way to get one okay all
right first picture is what tell me you
have two smiling man okay what does it
mean it says what do the signs feel like
in sign so the first the first level of
understanding the signs of a Buddha is
that if you have certain emotions in
your heart they're gonna be reflected on
your face okay like and that's just
obvious you know that's not like some
philosophy thing if your heart is clear
and your mind is clear and you feel
happy then obviously you're gonna smile
okay and and that's just a basic thing
Buddhism goes further and says that the
emotions that you had leading into this
life created your particular face okay
every detail of your appearance was
created by yourself
according to if you yelled at your kids
last life or not not last week okay so I
thought the first meditation we do is
this one and what I'd like to do is is
have you take something about your
appearance that you like okay like a lot
of us like to not like our parents and
that's okay okay 99% you can dislike
your appearance but tonight for the
first meditation I'm gonna sit here I
want you to choose one thing about your
appearance is that okay if I sit here
it's gone
I want you to pick something about your
parents that you like okay
could be your smile could be your ears
you know okay
could be her finger okay you're gonna
choose something about your appearance
that you like okay
and I know a lot of people like to not
like their appearance but tonight you
have to think of something you enjoy
about your appearance okay and we're
gonna meditate on it and I want you to
try to guess what might have caused it
what kind of emotion inside of you might
have caused it if I say something that
you enjoy about your own appearance was
caused by a good thing inside of you
I'd like you to take a guess of what it
was okay and it might have been from
last night okay like maybe you don't
have it anymore I don't know maybe
probably you do have some women okay
when you get your nose you get some of
the old emotions you used to have - okay
so we're gonna sit up straight ready and
you know you might as well get used to
meditating and insurance it's useful why
do Buddhists sit on the ground and cross
their legs and notice there were no
chairs in India at those times I'm not
kidding the point of meditation is to
park your body so you don't have to
think about it if you park it in a way
that hurts you'll start thinking about
it so get as comfortable as you can sit
up straight I'll say it sit on your edge
of your chair if you can and don't put
your back on them it's good to turn your
cell phone off that Lord Buddha said
that was the first preliminary - you
don't believe me Francis he did okay
that's how we don't disturb the other
people in the audience tonight okay and
it's the first preliminary you should
always do - a meditation sit up straight
relax your forehead try to relax your
forehead if you have to cough coughs now
coughing sniff is good first relax your
eyelids
relax the corners of your mouth make
them saw try not to fidget because then
it'll disturb other people here
pull in your lower abdomen slightly
which helps you to straighten your spine
push your shoulders back just a bit
bring your shoulder blades closer
together in the back don't press your
lips together make them very loose relax
your fingers you can put them in some
meditation posture if you like touch
your first finger and your thumb chin
mudra and then slowly come to your
breath and start watching your breath
long relaxed exhales inhale will take
care of itself
and just watch your long exhales
and then please think of something about
your appearance that your your enjoy it
brings you happiness it could be your
smile could be your eyes could be the
way you stand could be your complexion
one thing about your physical appearance
that you enjoy brings you happiness I
think a smile is very typical
and then please try to relate it to some
feeling some good feelings that you have
perhaps it's a joy in the case of a
smile or kindness patience see see what
comes up in your mind automatically like
what if if it's true that some emotion
inside of me causes this part of my
appearance that I enjoy
then what emotion would it be and go
through some different sweet emotions
and see if you can try to guess what
might have caused your smile or your
complexion or your body type or your
eyes whenever it is you enjoy about your
body and will be quiet for a minute or
two
then please come back to your breath
watch three long exhales please don't
move until we finish three long exhales
and then you can take a stretch okay
good so it's not hard to imagine that
maybe your smile came from I don't know
being happy inside or maybe even your
eyes if they're clear might have come
from some kind of mental clarity or
kindness there's a deeper level in
Buddhism when we talk about that what a
Buddhist body look like and when you
hear the word Buddhist body and
personally I don't encourage you to
think about paintings you've seen from
Tibet where he has a huge bump on his
head and his ears are too long and where
he's got a big belly or something like
that I more think of times I went to
Paris on the bridges and they have these
golden angels up on the pillars or in
Mexico City the approach to the Congress
and there's a mile of angel statues on
the top of pillars or something like
that at the point of Buddhist body is
that when you reach it it will be the
most delicious beautiful thing you can
imagine okay
I used to encourage my students to read
Vogue magazine and pick out which one
they want to be you know but the point
about a Buddhist body physical body
which is where we're at right is that
it's the most exquisite thing you can
imagine so you have to try to think of
you know for me its wings and a certain
beautiful face and and just perfect
physically exquisite okay and that's
that's what you should have in mind when
you're talking about a Buddhist body at
this point in the sutra is talking about
the physical appearance of an
enlightened being and if you have sweet
emotions going on inside of you for
lifetimes it affects how you look and
affects how you feel so right now Cebu
tea is talking about
physical appearance of a person who's
abouna okay
now I'd like you to go deeper and if I
tell you it was some action of some
habitual action that you do towards
other people has created the qualities
of your appearance okay then I we're
gonna do a second meditation again I'd
like you to choose something about your
appearance that you enjoy and I know
every all of us think we way too much
and you know we all have a list of
things we don't like about our physical
appearance but tonight I'd like you to
do the opposite I'd like you to you know
the people who really love you who are
maybe sitting next to you or in front of
you they they see certain beautiful
things about your appearance you know I
I have close people to me and they're
always telling me oh that's so nice and
I don't think so but they think so you
seen I mean so try to think of a person
who loves you a lot and and then
something about you that they often say
you know I like the way you work your
smile or I like the way you blink or you
know try to think of some one who really
loves you and even when they really love
you they see you in a different way than
even than you do and they will say oh
you have the nicest eyes so I like your
eyebrows or you know your little fingers
are so nice or something like that okay
and it's not the image we have of
ourselves right but it's perhaps the
image that someone who really loves you
handsome of you okay and you know that
there are people like that at least your
mom okay so try to think of something
about your parents that you learn but in
this meditation we're gonna go deeper
and we're gonna assume that there was
some kind of habitual actions that you
used to do towards other people that
created this kind of beauty in you okay
the beauty that you have so it was
something and that's the way it is okay
there's no accidents the world isn't the
result of a
of an accidental explosion from nothing
which is anyway impossible you know your
there's reasons for the way you look
there's reasons for where you were born
the where what family you were born into
everything has a reason and it all goes
down to how did you treat other people
in the past okay so I want you to we're
gonna sit and meditate again and I
wanted again focus on the one part for
me I have us I know I like I like my
smile I don't like much else about me I
like this you know let's see the smile
and say at least I smile you know even
when I'm not even when I'm grumpy some
take something you like about yourself
I'm gonna move the tree over here I
guess Scott is that good and pick the
same thing about yourself and this time
I want you to try to guess we call
correlation right those of you who are
Buddhists it's called correlation it
means what action
what habitual action did you do in your
past life by the way if it was that
habitual to create your your nose or
your lips it was you're probably still
doing it okay so what action of kindness
towards other people might have created
your the thing about you your appearance
which is most beautiful okay got it
what kind of action what habitual action
that you did you do very often in your
past life probably you're still doing
something similar that might have caused
it you ready okay same drill sit up
straight
make sure yourself once off in
Guadalajara we charge people $50 if it
rings in the talk and suddenly it never
rang anymore
feet flat on the floor do your throat
clearing no
sniffle now then relax your lips make
them very relaxed find your center of
gravity you know move up a bit move back
a bit
left right find the centre push your
shoulders back a little bit pull in your
stomach slightly relax your eyelids
little smile Mona Lisa meditation smile
and come to your breath and start
watching your breath just focus on the
exhales don't worry about the Indians
now please bring your mind to something
about your appearance that you you enjoy
and I know a lot of us may not think
that we're handsome or beautiful but
what's one nice thing everybody has a
few nice things their eyes or their
eyelids or their eyebrows their chin or
something beautiful
and then please try to like
free-associate think kind of out of the
box
what kind of habitual action might have
caused the color of your eyes or the
shape of your lips or your chin or your
arms something you enjoy
I'll give you Clues like nice arms come
from reaching out and helping other
people when they need it
nice lips come from encouraging other
people you know bright eyes come from
helping other people to understand
things
what's a something I might have done to
cause the part of me that I most enjoy
what kindness did I do towards others
that created this part of me
then please come back to your breath
watch your breath three long breaths
and slowly open your eyes take a stretch
how many people heard me do the pen
before raise your hand did anybody not
hear me do the pen before yeah okay just
for you to understand your body and a
Buddhist body you have to understand the
pen so I know you heard it a thousand
times my teacher said you had to hear at
three thousand times so you still have
two hundred and ninety and some to go
okay and I'll do it quick okay just so
you don't suffer to it but I haven't
found a better way to explain seeds okay
so here we go I'll ask you questions
give me answers don't be shy okay what
is this thing yeah if a small dog comes
up here you know on the stage and I go
like mmm and it's a puppy dog what will
they do with it yeah they will chew it
okay so does the dog see this as a pen
how did they see it Francis they see
something to chew on right now Francis
you gotta answer me serious okay not
like Uncle Mike who's right the dog or
the human the dog thinks is something
that you the human thinks it's a pen
whose right
dad yeah but the dog can chew it's okay
and the human can write with it okay
now we go to emptiness okay ready I put
the thing here black thing all the dogs
leave the room you're gonna have any
fresh mist by the way okay I don't know
who's paying for it but we're still
working that out all the humans leave
the room to get refreshments all the
dogs leave the room the room is empty
nobody's here Francis come on you can
help me on all the dogs left the room
all the people left the room Francis was
the last one out he closed the door at
that time is this a pen or something to
chew on
which one Francis going to I don't know
okay that's gin Utah okay that's
emptiness coaching okay
it really is honestly there's no more
complicated than that we can put all the
Buddhist philosophers out of business if
if people just learn the pen okay
there's nothing and it's not incorrect
and there's nothing there's nothing left
out that chandrakirti explained later
okay it's it's just that okay when the
people leave and the dogs leave it's
neither a pen or a chew toy it's just a
black stick it's waiting to be something
okay now I'm the first person come back
in the room I'm like looking at Nancy
over there who's just walked in and I
glanced down at this thing at that
moment what does it become pen if it
just became a pen when I looked at it
then it's that pen coming from me or
come from the pen it must be for me
because if the dog walked in it would
become a tutorial that proves that it's
coming from my mind there's something
coming from my mind okay
we can confirm it I can stand here I can
wish that it was a big diamond and there
we go
let's try
it's called positive thinking what are
youcome no way to call it the secret
what did you got Law of Attraction okay
get serious no I'll split with the money
with you still a pen okay is it coming
from my mind yes we proved that is it
coming from what I want no you can't
just want if you could just want it it
would come from your mind then nobody
would be poor and no one's husband would
be anyway okay so it's that doesn't
that's not how it works so how does it
really work there's a seed in your mind
and when the seed opens this is cool and
if you meditate a lot you can watch it
happen a small image comes into your
mind from a seed in your mind the seed
is called what or you can call it karma
okay and I hate to use the word Karma
because it's so confusing but there's a
small seed in your mind it it it opens
and then a small image comes up in your
mind and your mind watches the image and
and your mind projects it out onto this
black thing and the human has a seed for
a pen and the dog has a seed for a chew
toy and that's why they see different
things okay and that's why you see
everything in your life okay including
your nose and your eyes and your lips
okay now so we're gonna go deeper
that's the third meditation okay you've
heard it said that Buddhist think that
you know your arm is not Michael and all
of Michael's parts are not Michael and
Michael's not not is Armand Michael's
not not as parts okay this is supposed
to be profound it's just confusing okay
like okay I understand I'm not my arm
cuz I got two arms I can't be two people
I understand
I'm not unconnected to my arm because if
I am I'm not me anymore and I understand
I'm not something I'm not the camera but
when you say in Buddhism that I'm not
all the parts of me together that
makes sense to me you see it I mean but
Buddhism says that you are not all the
parts of you together okay
what that means is there's always one
more part that has to be thrown into the
mix before you become you can you guess
what it is
it's that picture that comes out in your
mind you see this these two parts are
not a pen until I walk up and a seat
opens in my mind and in a small pen
picture comes out and it goes on the
thing and then it becomes a pen is it
real or not yeah it's real anybody
doesn't think so
come up here and get a mustache unless
you already have one okay I mean it's
real okay and then there's a joke in the
monastery they said you're not allowed
to say if you say it's real even though
it's coming from my mind they hit you
you thought rosaries were for prayers
right I had a friend he was actually a
director of the Oriental division of New
York public he said can I go to your
monastery I said yeah but you know don't
get upset if you see some weird stuff he
said I can go and he came to a monster
the first day he saw a monkey
disciplined with a rosary
then you get this dots across her
forehead and he left he left the next
day he couldn't take it okay so anyway
if you want to get those dots across
your forehead in their monastery you can
say even though the Pens coming from my
mind it's still real then you get hit
what are you supposed to say yeah
because it's kind of her in mind it's
real okay got it
so why do I see a pen because I have a
pen seen I must have done something in
the past
I must have shared what I have with
other people okay and that puts a seat
how's the seed planted kids how's the
seed plant I reach out and give you a
pen I put a pen seat in my mind how does
it happen I see my hand open I see my
hand open it's like when I yell at the
kids you are the worst
in New York and I hear it then that puts
an impression on my mind and and if I
see myself let go that puts a pen scene
in my mind then you know like two two
years later somebody gives me a pen
understand everything is created by
seeds in my mind including your nose and
your nips got it
were you born with them no what did
Buddha just ask to Booty if someone has
the signs are there Buddha what did
somebody say I'm gonna lose half of you
I don't care what it's the Buddha say no
why then he said they're impossible okay
it means you weren't born with them
seeds are coming out of your mind
how many per second 65 per finger-snap
seeds are opening in your mind and
maintaining fingers and nose and eyes
you see you weren't born with them
they're being produced every millisecond
by your own mind they're being sustained
like a fountain by the karmic seat in
your mind okay
the day you stop taking in poor people
refugees immigrants you can cut the
fountain off and the prosperity of your
country will dying you see the day you
stop helping other countries the day you
say you're bad and I'm good
then then you cut off your all your
prosperity all your happiness it's it's
it's unbelievable you see what I mean so
you have to keep helping other people
you don't have a choice you want to keep
the nose like the eye then you have to
keep doing what you did otherwise you
will die you see is it possible being
immortal if this is true is it possible
to me immortal how keep helping other
people that's all it's very interesting
what's sustaining your arms and your
fingers and your legs and your face and
your nose and your eyes is kindnesses
you did in the past people and when you
stop doing them you will lose them
and it's called Darrin or illness okay
it's very interesting so in this system
what you call it it's a pyramid system
you have to keep giving back so the next
meditation is and then maybe we take a
break the next meditation is about how
do you say you see you can have all the
parts of a Buddha you can have the arms
of a Buddha you can have the wings of an
angel you can have this angelic face you
can have a heavenly form made of light
you see that's a Buddha but unless you
have the seeds in your mind you can't
tie it together the seeds in your mind
glue stuff together you see what I mean
are all your parts all are are all of
flosses parts floss no not until the
image comes out and glues them all
together so all the coherence if that's
a difficult idea
anything that makes sense in your life
that's not crazy insane war killing
unkindness it's all coming from a
certain kind of karmic seed in you
anything that makes sense
anything that's comforting anything
that's predictable any system that's
working anything in your life that's
working it's flowing out of seeds in
your mind you see and when you stop
being kind to others then those that
flow will stop and then the world
becomes chaotic is it really wait is it
really chaotic it is it's coming from
you okay it is chaotic give me air come
get a mustard
yeah it's a getting okay well who made
it chaotic you did okay if you see chaos
in the world it's you what makes things
coherent what glues things together is
it's the responsibility of being kind to
others that's all that creates all
all the things in your life that are not
crazy come from that okay got it
so we're gonna do one more meditation
the goal of this meditation is to stop
thinking you were born with a nice nose
or you were born with the right color
eyes you know or or your ears are okay
okay the goal of this meditation is to
stop thinking that you were born with
those things cuz you weren't okay you
have seeds in your mind they are opening
at a rate of 65 per second
they are creating your impression of
your nose and your eyes and whatever
else you like about yourself it's being
sustained by nice things you did to
other people okay so notice where we
went in the meditation what was the
first one I have a nice smile because
I'm happy inside halfway true okay what
was the second one I have a nice smile
cuz yeah because I made the other people
happy okay what's the third one
oh sorry I should have said in the
second one I was born within my smile
because I made other people happy what's
the third one my mom now it's sustained
by my current kindnesses you see and if
I stop it will die I will loosen
it's called done okay if I stop being
kind if I stop if I turn the water off
on the fountain the fountain is called
your life and your appearance and it's
impermanent and there's a limited number
see it but if you stop making seeds if
you if you tell these people you can't
come to my country you know you you
you're dying in the room next door I
don't care I'm going to lock the door
you know you I don't care then that's
the best way to die okay you will lose
up you'll use up your seeds you don't
create new ones and it stops okay if
this theory is correct the dumbest thing
you can do
to hurt other people or to refuse to
help them okay got it
okay so we're gonna do a meditation this
is called coherent meditation okay and
it means okay you have a you have a nose
that's created by a certain kind of
actions and you have a ears and you have
lips
but what glues them together you know
and by the way you can lose this and
then they call you Alzheimer's or they
lose coherence they can't glue things
together anymore words the phonemes and
the sinan you know they don't make sense
anymore to people the the sounds are the
same but something inside of them that
glues the sounds into speech they lose
or it's something that glues their
child's face into someone they recognize
is lost and that's coherence
you see that's kindness kindness is the
coherence kindness is the Karma that
glues all the parts of your life
together and when you stop being kind it
breaks it down got it so we're gonna do
a meditation this is the third one the
picture is the granion
somebody in China gave me this beautiful
statue and what is it that's gluing all
your parts together why are you not
senile what do you call what's
Alzheimer's there's another one yeah why
don't you have dementia right now you
know
it's because you still have old seeds of
kindness okay and when you lose them you
will get dementia you see and then
things fall apart there's nothing to
glue things together the reason you can
put together your right arm and your
left arm and to call you the reason you
can glue together a top of a pen and the
bottom of a pen is only that you've been
nice to other people got it
that's coherent got it cool and and by
the way if you purposely if you believe
this and you purposely you go out
tomorrow nice now I'm gonna be more kind
thing more other people because I want
to have a coherent life
things will change around you
drastically things will happen in your
life weird stuff you know weird
impossible things will start to happen
and it's very exciting because you get
some kind of confirmation
you know like weird impossible things
someone hands you three million dollars
we built this cafeteria it that he
worked on it yeah somebody just stay
here here's the moon
tell me what you need I said three
million dollars yeah okay build it you
know it's very beautiful we redid the
whole you know anyway
if you are it's real if you practice it
real things happen to you okay
got it and if you don't you lose what
you have okay here we go
sit up straight last meditation before
the break and refreshments wherever
they're coming from actually you made
the refreshments if you don't like them
it's your fault
if you don't like this talk is your
fault if you do like this talking sin my
fault okay let's go sit up straight
relax your nerves
bring to mind the part of you that you
enjoy and could be your something about
your physical appearance by the way it's
not my fault that's where they started
in the Sutra we'll go to your mind later
and try to think what pattern of
thinking isn't that I've been doing most
of my life that allows my mind to glue
together the images which appear in
front of it what is it that I've done
towards others my whole life
that has allowed me to see my left arm
connected to my right arm and my eyes
and my nose on my face what is it that
allows me to perceive that and it's
kindness it's a pattern of maybe it's
imperfect kindness but your whole life
you've been attracted to helping other
people and that's why you can see your
face in a mirror that's why you can walk
or drive or learn is only because of
those seeds those seeds make your life
coherent the entire life together if you
didn't have those seeds you would be
what we call senile or or insane so here
we go appreciate the proof of your
kindness you have a face you have a body
and it was created it was glued together
by kindness towards others so try to
think about it think about kindness as
you do and try to understand and it
keeps your world from being chaos
please come back to your breath three
long breaths three long exhales don't
move yet
and then relax take a strategy one last
thing before your refreshments my
Spanish my Mexican friends call me Senor
el tema causa one more thing mr. one
more thing
there's a famous concept in Buddhism
called ma jamika which is middle way
okay and at this point in the Sutra Lord
Buddha explains the word middle way
sorry I thought it'd be nice thing to
leave with you with in case you run away
during the break somehow happens
sometimes so what is middle way mean in
Buddhism and it's very famous you know
the highest school of Buddhism is called
middle way madam and what does it mean
and it comes from the next question in
the Sutra and the Buddha says yes sir
Bertie you're right people who have
those signs that only Buddhists have are
not Buddhist it doesn't make them
Buddhist okay now you know the punch
line you know what makes them Buddhist
is that coherent karma being kind to
others you see so it doesn't help you if
you have the signs that only Buddha's
have on their body because you can't see
yourself as a Buddha unless you've
treated other people like a Buddha you
seen I mean it's very interesting you
could have all the signs in your body
and not see yourself as a Buddha if you
haven't treated other people as a Buddha
because you wouldn't be able to glue the
signs together in your mind okay got it
just nod or you don't get refreshments
then then Buddha says you're right
savuti you know you gave a good answer
and you should be aware therefore that
the signs on the body of a Buddha are
deceptive so according to Buddhism the
whole world is tricking you there's
something about the world this tricking
you and I'm going to tie it back to the
two husbands
okay so there's something about the
appearance of the husband when he yells
at you especially when you feel anger or
when you feel upset there's something
tricking you about the husband what is
it but what is what does it appear to be
what what appears to be going on he
appears to be wanting to criticize you
you see he appears to have decided that
he will call you stupid so just before
you learn legit another kitty nice
abandon they say very famous just before
he yelled at you stupid he must have had
the thought my wife is stupid okay then
then you feel like that's why he's
calling you stupid
and that's deceptive that's tricking you
okay
appearances are tricking you you want
Maya you on illusion in Buddhism it's
your husband when he when he says you're
stupid you know because it looks like he
decided to call you stupid but what's
really going on yeah you called your
kids stupid last week okay this you
planted a seed by hearing yourself and
the seed open to noise you know when you
open the door when you got home to see
dolphin okay now illusion in Buddhism
means it looks like your husband decided
to call you stupid and it looks like
that's why he called you stupid but well
it's really happening is a seed is
opening in your mind you are watching a
husband coming from your own mind okay
and that's that's deception so Buddha
says to Cebu d don't forget middle way
don't forget to stay in the middle way
and what that means is don't swing this
way and don't swing this way this way
means my husband is decided to call me
stupid
that's deception it looks like he
decided to say something bad to you or
someone hurt you right they decided to
hurt you that's this extreme what's the
other extreme
the other stream is something like by
the way everything is your phone there's
nothing that's not your phone
how's that but the other extreme is this
is a rare extreme relatively rare this
extreme everyone falls into my husband
decided to yell at me my friend decided
to hurt me you know that country decided
to hurt my country that's this extreme
okay then this extreme is if it's not
that way it doesn't exist okay
and that's a very rare extreme and it's
it's very rare it's people who got a bad
explanation of emptiness from somebody
somebody bla blog for an hour and
everybody went home and said nothing
matters I can yell at my husband now the
Lama said he's empty yeah you know no
that's very common unfortunately that's
the other extreme middle way is one and
if you give me a middle way I'll almost
give you a brain what's the middle way
yeah it's real and it's coming cuz I
yelled at my kids last week that's all
you know it's coming cuz there's
something I did last week okay that's
all that avoids this extreme of thinking
your husband decided to do something to
you it avoids this extreme was thinking
if your husband's coming from you it
must somehow be unreal he's not unreal
he's real why because he is coming from
you okay do you live in your head I
better tell you that before the break
because you might go home no the answer
is no you are projecting a world and in
that outer world the husband exists okay
some person in Beijing was very
concerned she disrupted a program for
like 10 minutes because she said that
means when I kissed my husband I'm
kissing myself right
I said no no no middle way middle way
he's coming from you but he's real he's
out there he's coming from you out there
okay so it's real okay
so we've basically you didn't notice but
we finished four meditations the first
one is where some part of your
appearance reflects your how you feel
inside like your smile reflects your
happiness and that's sort of a shallow
level of karma and then we went deeper
and we said that something you did for
other people has created your body in
your face okay and then we went deeper
and we said that you know seeds coming
out of your mind glue yourself together
and without them you might lose your
sense of self and that happens to people
it wears out and then I snuck one in on
you you didn't really notice but it was
middle way that was meditation number
four and that came from a statement by
Lord Buddha to Cebu T when he said are
you ready for this he said everything is
deceptive about your body when you
become a Buddha everything's deceptive
about your body and things which insofar
as things don't exist they're not a
deceptive okay which means that you can
treat the nice parts of your body like
you treated the second husband okay so
to misunderstand your nose or
misunderstand your eyes means to think
they didn't come from being kind to
other people and the eyes that you
possess that didn't come from being kind
to others and I don't know anything
about you that didn't come from some
from being kind to someone else doesn't
exist like the second husband okay
that's why I did the husband first
tomorrow I don't know what I'm gonna do
[Music]
but every part of you is just like those
two husbands you can look at yourself
and and think that you came from what
you eat or came from where you went to
school or from your parents you can
think that but if you think that
everything about you came from how you
treat other people then you'll have a
deeper understanding of yourself okay
so Lord Buddha in the fourth meditation
is saying that stick to a middle path
don't think that anything in your life
is not coming from being kind to other
people okay
just nod okay the next meditation fifth
meditation do you have those up there
you showing us number five which would
be the lady in the party dress okay at
this point in his commentary by the way
all Buddha's are split into two parts
okay do you know this thing physical
body and and what we call Dharma body
okay so physical body means how a Buddha
looks like an angel
okay physical side of a Buddha and then
there's a mental side of a Buddha which
means how a Buddha things okay and if
you want to know how a Buddha thinks
it's very much connected to the two
husband's okay and that's how Buddhist
thing you know Buddha walks into a room
they're already thinking about this the
second husband okay
like that's how Buddhists think and the
idea is very beautiful how Buddhists
think create their body okay how so
there's two parts to a Buddha one called
Dharma body and one called foreign body
and the physical appearance of a Buddha
is direct result of how they think and
the fact that they have a body at all
it's like a girl getting ready for a
party
which is that love drives them to take a
physical form okay so the idea is that
Buddhists don't need a physical form
they don't need to
have a physical body but to help us they
take a physical body so I thought the
picture of a young lady who dressed up
for a party okay and the meditation here
which I'm not going to do because we're
running short on time but you can think
of the last time you dressed up okay and
how what was the motivation you had in
mind
and hopefully I mean you were going
someplace special like your sister's
wedding or your friend's wedding you
know and you put on a tie or you put on
a nice dress and that motivation to
dress up to make other people happy is
why a Buddha has a physical body okay
and that's the only reason you see it's
a very cool idea they don't have to have
a physical form they choose to put on a
dress to show themselves to people
because of loves the idea is that when
you do that meditation you're gonna
think about the reason of Buddha appears
in the world is only out of love they
choose to take a physical form out of
love want to go deeper you supposed to
say yeah in China yeah I tell people in
China people in China will go crazy and
jump up and down when you still want to
go deeper I said yeah in America they go
yeah man that's okay so the physical
body of a Buddha is divided into two
parts okay one is called coke classic
Buddha and that's standard exquisite
beautiful angelic form and that's what
they hang out with in their living room
in their underwear they're in their
Buddha body and it's you know exquisite
and have it be like wings and totally
exquisite body of light which is
immortal and then they have another
version of themselves that they send out
when people can use it like if a if a
lady would be kind
to her neighbor if her neighbor had a
dog the Buddha will emanate as the dunk
you see or if a person's at the seaside
Beach and they just broke up with their
boyfriend or something then Buddha will
emanate as a wave as the sound of a wave
and try to comfort the person with the
sound of a wave so but is not limited to
a to a body a normal body they can look
like your boss your sister your wife
your kids and they they very typically
will emanate as someone quite close to
you can or filmer because because then
they can help you so the closer the
relationship between two people
the more likely that one of them is a
Buddha and they will emanate then they
might be nice to you for 20 years and
then suddenly irritate you really bad
and they've been waiting 20 years which
is nothing for a Buddha to do something
irritating to improve you job just
telling you what's been going on so I'm
just kidding I know she's not your thing
but so they have two bodies one is
called their home body which is the one
they live in you know among Buddhists
and then there's their other body which
is the one they show in the world when
people need it and the cool thing about
that body is it's called some good -
about some good dupa means do you know
thunder what huh it's spontaneous
meaning they don't have any meditation
it just shows up if a lady in Los
Angeles would treat her neighbor better
if the neighbor had a dog the Buddha
shows up there as a dog without planning
to show up there it's it's spontaneous
from many millions of years of trying to
be nice to other people so when you
become a Buddha your body will just show
up whenever it's useful for someone you
see so that's kind of really
that's a kind of a really cool quality
okay and the next meditation after the
girl in the party dress is it says
Buddha jewel faces versus reflections
and it's a guy looking in the mirror
okay and you want to go deeper I gotta
take a picture for the Chinese this is
hard okay you asked for it then and it's
late and I'm sorry to do it to you late
but okay
somebody might enjoy it so so there's a
way to divide the bodies of a Buddha
into four okay and one is what I just
told you the body they hang out in in
their own living room in Buddha paradise
and that's like some angelic form made
of light never gets old always beautiful
second one is what yeah it's kind of
just shows up like if you walk in front
of a mirror or something you don't think
I want to reflect in this mirror you
walk in front of a mirror there's
somebody there right if as soon as the
Buddha exists
they're everywhere somebody could use
them like you walking in front of mirror
they don't think you don't get up and
you know standing from the mirror and
way for your reflection to show up and
you don't think I wish my face would
show up so I could shave it or something
you know like it just happens you think
so
Buddha second body is automatic when
someone needs them they're there okay
the body just appears that's the second
volume of Buddha third body is their
mind okay how they think and they're
very much into this idea of the second
husband okay they don't even see anymore
the husband who's not there they're out
of the habit of blaming anyone else for
their life okay they automatically
anything that happens to them they
automatically start thinking oh I must
have yelled at my kids last week okay
they don't even think anything else
they don't see anything else they never
see the second husband who's not there
okay
now the fourth body of a Buddha is kind
of complicated ready I'll ask you is
there anything about the first three
bodies that's not coming from their own
seats meaning say you can say for you is
there anything about your body or is
there anything about your mind which is
not coming from how you treated other
people in the past there's nothing that
fact is their fourth body the fact that
nothing about them doesn't come from how
they treat other people is their fourth
body and it's called truth and in
sanskrit that's dharma okay so that's
reality that the reality of their three
bodies is their fourth body okay the
fact that there's nothing about their
physical form or how they think that's
not coming from how they treated other
people
okay got it I gave a talk at Princeton
to the physics department and we were
talking about apparent contradictions in
both you know atomic theory small
particles and also macro series of where
the universe came from and I was
proposing that a lot of the apparent
paradoxes and physics could be solved by
believing in this system that things are
coming from your seeds and one guy
there's one guy in the back you know and
he was looking kind of what do you call
it skeptical here the whole thing and
then suddenly his face like like
brightened up you know and I and he said
can I ask you a question I said yeah he
said well according to what you just
said you know we kind of assumed
Newtonian Lee and an heiress thought a
little Aristotelian lee that the the
basic building block of realities atoms
and then he said according to you
according to what you're saying then the
underlying reality under that is
kindness and it's not particles that
make the world its kindness it's how you
behave towards other people and and I
was so blown away that he got it you
know that we live in a world where we
believe that the foundational the
foundation of all reality is atoms is
what do you call elements copper oxygen
iron and then they're saying he got it
right away he's like wow then you're
saying that the atoms come from kindness
and I said yeah and he said that solves
a lot of questions you know and it was
really cool so anyway that's another
book we have to write someday I went to
a guy in New York a recent trip here and
and he said he asked if he could publish
a book you know and I said well he said
what's the next book you're doing I'd
like to publish it and I sat in his
office in New York and he said uh I said
well I want to write this book called a
better history of time because the brief
history of time is the best-selling
English book in history you know and I
was said I want to write a better
history of time I want to correct what's
his name Steve I want to correct Steven
Hawkings and he said turn around and it
was always Stephen Hawking's books he
said I'm his publisher I said well I'm
still gonna write the book you know and
he was ok anyway so that guy looking at
himself in the mirror and the state of
mind which produces the physical bodies
right the lady who wants to dress up for
the party write her her intention to
dress up we call the Dharma bunny that's
the mind of a Buddha ok
that's the third body of a Buddha and
those of you who have been there
that's the first of the three jewels
okay so your Center in New York for the
last 20 years has been called three
jewels the first of the three jewels is
the Dharma jewel okay Buddha Joe and and
the Buddha jewel consists of those four
bodies
okay the motivation to be kind to people
the physical bodies that the girl puts
on when she wants to go out in the world
okay and the fact that they're not
coming from nowhere okay got it
just nod okay then the subject of the
book changes okay and I think we ever
I'm gonna go till 9:45 okay four more
minutes hang in there I could with
something in China challenge me they
said will you go all night I said yep
and we did anyway I'm not gonna do it to
you because they'll kick us out she's
nervous
but we can continue tomorrow but the
subject of the Sutra changes at this
point they've been talking about the
physical body of a Buddha and where it
comes from and then the answer is it
comes from a Buddhist state of mind and
the way a Buddha understands how things
happen so then Lord Buddha says you know
to Cebu T let's switch over to the the
cost of a Buddhist mind okay let's talk
about where the Dharma body comes from
okay let's talk about where the mind and
the emptiness of a Buddha come from
let's go deeper into the Dharma body
which is the second jewel okay so first
jewel is Buddha
Joe second jewel is Dharma John so
there's two ways to understand Dharma
jewel what is Joe mean by the way why do
we say what's it their entry in Buddha
and Buddha Joe you can say that
Buddhists like general Buddha guy
and Buddha jewel means what can yeah
refuge what can protect you
what is it about the Buddha that can
protect you okay can emptiness protect
you give me an example
huh yeah when you when you are about to
say no you're stupid and you hesitate
not because you're nice and not because
you're moral and not because you're
compassionate but because you understand
your plan to see for him again to be a
I'm not gonna say okay because you
control yourself
not because it's a nice thing to do but
because it's a harmful thing to do to
yourself you see you you refuse to call
him stupid not because he's not stupid
he is stupid we know that but you refuse
to put it into words why he will be
stupid again the next day you see and
that's refuge that's the idea of
Cerritos okay so the three jewels is
tied up with the two husband okay you
protect yourself if you stop hurting
other people got it and it's you can't
hurt another person it's not possible if
they have seeds you can hurt them but
they made the seeds not you okay it's
very interesting so anyway at this point
the suture changes there are four great
subjects so far first one Sibelius Lord
Buddha what do you want me to do with my
life
Buddha says help other people get
enlightened okay second one the second
one is interesting he says how do I do
that and Buddha said six perfections six
ways of acting towards other people
what's the first one giving so then the
Buddha before we did it last year the
Buddha goes off on how to give things
what's the main thing stop thinking
they're coming from their own side
understand that the person you're going
to give something to and understand the
person who's giving it which is you and
understand the thing you're giving them
are all flowing out of your own mind
okay then you can really give things to
people we finished that last year okay
then the questions about the physical
body boo-boo we finished you are
graduates of physical body of the Buddha
now we go on next to the mental body of
a Buddha who created the Dharma body of
a Buddha what is it consistent
okay what's the Dharma jewel what can
what can protect you huh you're just
understanding the two husbands
that's Dharma jewel okay that's Dharma
that understanding is what we call
Dharma is it the books is this Dharma
jewel can it protect you
yeah we say pretty good okay diamond
cutter citrus pretty good right you can
call it we call it when you call it
couldn't dock thinking it's called it's
called not bad Dharma jewel
it's the sutras okay but the real Dharma
jewel is to understand your husband that
to understand who is not is the ultimate
dharma jewel okay why because it
protects you that's the that's what the
that's what the three jewels do okay so
tomorrow we have to get into the Dharma
body and commoner Sheila has some very
far-out ideas about it okay what is the
what is the body of them what is them
how does a Buddha thing you know so
physically it's okay you know I'm gonna
be angelic like the statues in Paris you
know but mentally what am I gonna be
we're gonna get into that tomorrow which
is the Dharma jewel okay don't look so
confused you make me feel guilty okay
see you tomorrow okay thank you okay
[Applause]